<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Description of Center for Advanced Judaic Studies Library, Halper 346: Court document</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Center for Advanced Judaic Studies Library</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/">These images and the content of Center for Advanced Judaic Studies Library, Halper 346: Court document are free of known copyright restrictions and in the public domain. See the Creative Commons Public Domain Mark page for usage details, http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/.</licence>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode">Metadata is ©2017 University of Pennsylvania Books &amp; Manuscripts and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution License version 4.0 (CC-BY-4.0 https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode. For a description of the terms of use see the Creative Commons Deed https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>A legal document in Judeo-Arabic and legal Hebrew-Aramaic, issued in the court of Daniel, titled here here הנשיא הגדול ראש גליות כל ישראל, identical to the title bestowed on Daniel in a Ḳetubah dated one month before this document, in London, British Library Or. 5561B fol. 2, and a few months later in Cambridge T-S 13J 13 fol. 11. See Mann, the Jews of Egypt, vol. I p. 175; The autograph signatures of the clerks of the court, serving here as witnesses, Abraham ha-kohen ben Aaron and Mevorakh ben Nathan he-ḥaver. The latter appears in Genizah documents, as a clerk, judge and scribe in the court of Fustat, between 1150, serving under his father, until 1181, when he served under Maimonides; He appears in the list of judges assembled by S. D. Goitein, A Mediterranean Society vol. II Appendix D, no. 22. The content of the document appears to be in his hand. Compare to Cambridge T-S 13J 1 fol. 21 (dated 1150); The autographs of the judges: Jacob ha-Kohen ben Joseph (found on documents dated 1161-1164, the period preceding that of Maimonides), Menaḥem ben Berakhot and Menasheh ben Joseph, a member of Maimonides'court, 1164-1199. See Goitein, ibid. nos. 19, 27; Testimony that the seven dinar given by Abu'l-Ala ben Asbu Sahl al-Jubaili to Abul'Ma'ali the merchant as a pledge, has been taken from him, he is thus acquitted of any claim. The latter is also known as Samuel ben Judah ibn Asad.</note>
        <note>Condition: nearly complete, damaged; verso, save scribblings in Arabic, is blank.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <country>United States</country>
            <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
            <institution>University of Pennsylvania</institution>
            <repository>Center for Advanced Judaic Studies Library</repository>
            <collection>Cairo Genizah Collection</collection>
            <idno type="call-number">Halper 346</idno>
            <altIdentifier type="resource">
              <idno>https://franklin.library.upenn.edu/catalog/FRANKLIN_9940420243503681</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary/>
            <textLang mainLang="jrb" otherLangs="heb arc">Judeo-Arabic; Hebrew; Official Aramaic (700-300 BCE); Imperial Aramaic (700-300 BCE)</textLang>
            <msItem>
              <title>Court document</title>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <support>
                  <p>Parchment</p>
                </support>
                <extent>28 X 26 cm </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout>Columns: 1; lines: 26 (25 text, 1 signature) (recto); ruling method: left rule justified by stretching last character.</layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>Hebrew Arabic Oriental semi-cursive</scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
            <decoDesc>
              <decoNote>Material applied: black ink</decoNote>
            </decoDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate/>
              <p>June-July 1164</p>
              <origPlace>Fustat</origPlace>
            </origin>
            <provenance>Cairo Genizah Collection (University of Pennsylvania. Center for Advanced Judaic Studies. Library).</provenance>
            <provenance>Cairo Genizah Collection (Dropsie College. Library).</provenance>
            <provenance>Amram.</provenance>
          </history>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords n="subjects">
          <term>Acquittals</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <surface n="1r">
      <graphic height="7598px" url="master/4712_0000.tif" width="6592px"/>
      <graphic height="190px" url="thumb/4712_0000_thumb.jpg" width="165px"/>
      <graphic height="1800px" url="web/4712_0000_web.jpg" width="1562px"/>
    </surface>
    <surface n="1v">
      <graphic height="7598px" url="master/4712_0001.tif" width="6592px"/>
      <graphic height="190px" url="thumb/4712_0001_thumb.jpg" width="165px"/>
      <graphic height="1800px" url="web/4712_0001_web.jpg" width="1562px"/>
    </surface>
  </facsimile>
</TEI>
