<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Description of British Library, Harley Ch 43 A 66 B: Latin quitclaim with Hebrew docket</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>contributor</resp>
          <persName>Ilana Tahan</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>cataloger</resp>
          <persName>Agata Paluch</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Polonsky Foundation</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>British Library</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/">These images and the content of British Library Harley Ch 43 A 66 B: Latin quitclaim with Hebrew docket are free of known copyright restrictions and in the public domain. See the Creative Commons Public Domain Mark page for usage details, http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/.</licence>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/legalcode">To the extent possible under law, British Library has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this metadata about British Library Harley Ch 43 A 66 B: Latin quitclaim with Hebrew docket. This work is published from: United States. For a summary of CC0, see https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/. Legal code: https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/legalcode.</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="relatedResource">Manuscript description based on Margoliouth, G.: Catalogue of the Hebrew and Samaritan Manuscripts in the British Museum, London 1965 and Olszowy-Schlanger, Judith. Hebrew and Hebrew-Latin Documents from Medieval England: a diplomatic and Palaeographical Study. Turnhout: Brill, 2015.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <country>United Kingdom</country>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <collection>Hebrew Manuscripts Digitisation Project</collection>
            <idno type="call-number">Harley Ch 43 A 66 B</idno>
            <altIdentifier type="resource">
              <idno>http://www.bl.uk/manuscripts/FullDisplay.aspx?ref=Harley_Ch_43_A_66_B</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier type="bl_website">
              <idno>https://www.bl.uk/hebrew-manuscripts</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>Latin quitclaim with Hebrew docket</summary>
            <textLang mainLang="he" otherLangs="la">Hebrew; Latin</textLang>
            <msItem>
              <title>Latin quitclaim with Hebrew docket</title>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <support>
                  <p>Parchment</p>
                </support>
                <extent>2 folios; 2 folios </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout>Columns: 1; ruled lines: 15; written lines: 15; Inserted into the fold of a Latin charter together with another parchment leaf (see Harley ch 43 A 66 A and Harley ch 43 A 66 C). The three are held together by two seals.</layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>Latin Gothic script and Hebrew Ashkenazi documentary script of the 13th century.</scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate when="1257"/>
              <p>1257</p>
              <origPlace>Unknown</origPlace>
            </origin>
            <provenance>Acquisition: The Harley Collection, formed by Robert Harley (b. 1661, d. 1724), 1st earl of Oxford and Mortimer, politician, and Edward Harley (b. 1689, d. 1741), 2nd earl of Oxford and Mortimer, book collector and patron of the arts. Edward Harley bequeathed the library to his widow, Henrietta Cavendish, née Holles (b. 1694, d. 1755) during her lifetime and thereafter to their daughter, Margaret Cavendish Bentinck (b. 1715, d.1785), duchess of Portland; the manuscripts were sold by the Countess and the Duchess in 1753 to the nation for £10,000 (a fraction of their contemporary value) under the Act of Parliament that also established the British Museum; the Harley manuscripts form one of the foundation collections of the British Library.</provenance>
          </history>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass/>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <surface n="1r">
      <graphic height="3583px" url="master/10250_0000.jpg" width="4822px"/>
      <graphic height="141px" url="thumb/10250_0000_thumb.jpg" width="190px"/>
      <graphic height="1337px" url="web/10250_0000_web.jpg" width="1800px"/>
    </surface>
    <surface n="1v">
      <graphic height="3722px" url="master/10250_0001.jpg" width="5750px"/>
      <graphic height="122px" url="thumb/10250_0001_thumb.jpg" width="190px"/>
      <graphic height="1165px" url="web/10250_0001_web.jpg" width="1800px"/>
    </surface>
  </facsimile>
</TEI>
